<?xml version="1.0"?>
<mobilegallery>
	<artwork>
		<id>01</id>
		<room>room4</room>
		<title>Maria at La Granja</title>
		<author>Joaquin Sorolla y Bastida</author>
		<description>1907
Size: 67 1/8 in. x 33 1/2 in. (170.5 cm x 85.1 cm)

Gift of Mr. Archer M. Huntington in memory of his mother, Arabella D. Huntington, 1925:1

Sorolla was the most internationally famous Spanish artist of his day. Early in his career, he was greatly influenced by the realism of Velazquez and other artists of the 17th-century Spanish Golden Age, but he spent much time in Paris in the years around 1900 and developed a particular talent for combining traditional Spanish painting with the new approaches of French Impressionism and Post-Impressionism.

Sorolla painted plein air portraits with great skill and success, starting with his family and later portraying even the king and queen of Spain. This portrait is of the artist's daughter at age 17, when she had recently recovered from tuberculosis. She is shaded by trees that are not shown in the painting, but the juxtaposition of cool shadows with glowing patches of light is one of the artist's trademarks, as is the deft manipulation of paint into thick impasto highlights.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/maria_en_la_granja.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>02</id>
		<room>room3</room>
		<title>Pair of Zuijin</title>
		<author>Artist Unknown</author>
		<description>18th century
Size: 45 1/2 in. x 18 1/2 in. x 15 in. (115.57 cm x 46.99 cm x 38.1 cm)
Gift of Captain Clayton L. Miller and the Asian Arts Council, 1979:18.1
Zuijin are Shinto protector deities modeled after two of the most powerful positions within the Heian period (794–1185) court, the Sa-daijin, "Minister of the Left," andU-daijin, "Minister of the Right," also the captain of the imperial bodyguards. 

They are characterized as two male courtiers of different age: the younger officer is depicted with his mouth closed, and his elder counterpart is shown with his mouth slightly open.  Zuijin are perceived as Shinto equivalents and manifestations of Buddhist Nio guardian deities, for both share the same closed- and open-mouth pairing, and both flank the entrances to a place of worship.

Each standing on top of a tiger pelt, these two sculpted figures are dressed in courtier's attire of the highest rank, with kanmuri court caps adorned with oikake semi-circular side blinders.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_300w/1979.18.1_1_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>03</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>The Young Shepherdess</title>
		<author>William-Adolphe Bouguereau</author>
		<description>1885
Size: 62 in. x 28 1/2 in. (157.5 cm x 72.4 cm)
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Edwin S. Larsen, 1968:82
Trained at the Royal Academy in Paris, Bouguereau became one of the most prolific and successful exhibitors at the Parisian Salon in the later 19th century. Like Realist painters including Courbet or Millet, he shared a passion for subjects drawn from rural life. Bouguereau’s rural figures, however, are always closer to the idealized shepherds and shepherdesses of classical pastoral poetry than to the earthy farmers more often depicted by the Realists.

Moreover, during the decades when the Realists and Impressionists developed their bold anti-academic styles, Bouguereau remained the principal proponent of traditional painting, and his works are characterized by the superbly drawn anatomy and high degree of finish seen here.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_300w/196882_1_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>04</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>The Penitent Saint Peter</title>
		<author>El Greco</author>
		<description>ca. 1590-1595
Size: 49 1/4 in. x 42 3/8 in. (125.1 cm x 107.6 cm)
Gift of Anne R. and Amy Putnam, 1940:76
One of El Greco’s most enduring devotional images, The Penitent Saint Peter was a subject to which the painter often returned, and this is one of at least six known versions of the composition. The painting depicts the repentant Saint Peter, distraught at having denied that he knew Christ when questioned on the eve of the crucifixion.

The saint is dramatically isolated, set against the dark trunk of a tree and lit by an ethereal light that emphasizes his soulful expression and posture. The scene in the background at left shows Mary Magdalene returning from Christ’s tomb: having received the news of Christ’s resurrection from an angel, she runs to tell Saint Peter.

This work is marked by a religious intensity that can be related to the concerns of the Counter-Reformation church. The biblical description of Saint Peter’s penitence in the days after the crucifixion was used by Counter-Reformation Catholics to justify the sacrament of penance or confession, which had been challenged by Protestantism. Devotional concerns aside, the canvas is a quintessential example of El Greco’s painterly virtuosity and of the poignant humanity of his figures.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/194076_1.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>05</id>
		<room>room4</room>
		<title>"All Victorious" Guanyin Bodhisattva</title>
		<author>Artist Unknown</author>
		<description>China, Yunnan province
Size: 9 1/4 in. x 4 11/16 in. x 2 5/8 in. (48.9 cm x 11.91 cm x 6.67 cm)
Museum purchase with funds provided by the Helen M. Towle Bequest
1941:83
Buddhist sculptures from southwestern China, like this example in the Museum’s collection, are exceptionally rare, especially when datable by inscription. The graceful standing figure can be identified as Guanyin, the bodhisattva of compassion, because of the figure of the Buddha Amitabha in the crown.

The character “Da” has been carved on each foot, which indicates that it was made for the royal family of the Dali Kingdom. The extensive inscription on the back of the garment reveals that the Emperor Duan Zhengxing paid for this sculpture to be made for his sons, to ensure their prosperity and the continuation of the family line. It is interesting to note that no esoteric or philosophical ideas of Buddhism were invoked by these patrons.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/194183_1_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>06</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>The Somnambulist</title>
		<author>Rufino Tamayo</author>
		<description>1954
Size: 39 1/2 in. x 31 1/2 in. (100.3 cm x 80 cm)
Anonymous gift, 1964:130
An avid collector, Tamayo acquired art that today forms the core of two museums in Mexico: one in Oaxaca that displays pre-Columbian art and another in Mexico City that presents modern and contemporary art. These interests are found in his own works, which incorporate traditional Mexican imagery, yet are infused with the spirit of contemporary Surrealism.

Tamayo created both easel paintings and large-scale murals. He was a contemporary of the Mexican muralists Diego Rivera, José Clemente Orozco, and David Alfaro Siqueiros, but he explored abstraction to an extent not attempted by these others. The Somnambulist reveals Tamayo’s interest in developing a highly original style in its rendering of a sleepwalker with angular Cubist shapes and bold hues of orange and blue.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/1964.130_0.jpeg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>07</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Ivory Pendant Necklace</title>
		<author>Artist Unknown</author>
		<description>19th century
Size: 12 in. x 8 in. x 2 3/4 in. (30.48 cm x 20.32 cm x 6.99 cm)
Transfer from of the Sana Art Foundation.
Worn by the royal class in Hawai‘i as a symbol of power and genealogical inheritance, this ivory pendant necklace (lei niho palaoa) is made of sperm whale tooth, sennit fiber, and human hair. The necklace, or lei, is constructed of miniature braids from the entwined hair of an elite, maternal woman, a material selected because it was seen as spiritually potent.

Similarly, the tooth of a beached whale, shaped and polished to form the pendant, would have been seen by native Hawai‘ians as a gift from the sea and gods. Sennit cordage, made in this region from natural fibers or coconut husks, was woven as a strong yet functional appendage and clasp for this weighty necklace.

Imbued with the power and essence, or mana, of the creator, this piece was passed on through native Hawaiian generations as a visual symbol of the legitimization and adornment of a powerful chief or ruler.

One of more than 900 works recently given to The San Diego Museum of Art by the Sana Art Foundation, this object is representative of the Museum’s commitment to collect art from African, Pacific, and Native American cultures.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/New_Image_copy_0_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>08</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>Lotus</title>
		<author>Zhang Daqian</author>
		<description>1958
Size: 52 3/8 in. x 26 3/4 in. (133.03 cm x 67.95 cm)
Gift of Ambassador and Mrs. Everett F. Drumright, 1986:44
Zhang Daqian emerged as an acclaimed painter during the first half of the twentieth century– tumultuous and war-stricken years when China was striving to become a modern nation. Schooled in traditional ink painting, the artist adapted his style to modern sensibilities and was inspired by the work of abstract expressionists in the West. 

Zhang is most noted for the "splashed-ink-and-room" painting style that he did not develop until nearly 60 years of age. The lotus flower was one of his favorite subjects. Here the leaves come to life as bold, spontaneous splashes of ink, and the crisply delineated stems slice dynamically through the composition.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_300w/1986.44_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>09</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Portrait of a Man</title>
		<author>Giorgione</author>
		<description>Probably 1506
Size: 11 7/8 in. x 10 1/8 in. (30.2 cm x 25.7 cm)
Gift of Anne R. and Amy Putnam, 1941:100
The principal masterpiece of The San Diego Museum of Art's collection of Italian paintings, Giorgione’s Portrait of a Man (often identified as the Terris Portrait after the name of a former owner) is indeed one of the greatest Renaissance portraits in the United States.

The work epitomizes what Vasari called the modern manner, in which Giorgione sought to paint living and natural things. In a notable contrast to the sculptural surfaces common in fifteenth-century painting, Giorgione’s brushstrokes lack precise detail but surpass those of all earlier painters in their ability to describe warm flesh and soft hair.

The composition is closely cropped around the head of the sitter, and the setting or props often used to animate portrait paintings are absent, but the man’s turning gaze and ambiguous expression nonetheless make the work wholly engaging and alive. His somber demeanor seems to be emphasized by the dark tonality of the work, but technical examination has revealed that his now-black jacket was painted with blue and red pigments that have darkened with time: this serious man was originally seen in a flamboyant purple garment.
		</description> 
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/1941100_0_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>10</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Female Nude Reading</title>
		<author>Robert Delaunay</author>
		<description>1915
Size: 54 in. x 42 3/8 in. (137.2 cm x 107.6 cm)
Museum purchase through the Earle W. Grant Acquisition Fund, 1979:20
Single-minded in his pursuit of a pure pictorial language based on bold chromatic contrasts, Delaunay turned away from the muted Cubist palette of Picasso and Braque and looked instead to the lessons of Matisse and his followers, who had pioneered an expressive and deliberately dissonant use of room. The critic Guillaume Apollinaire used the term “Orphic,” a poetic label meant to evoke the work’s “cosmic” character, to describe Delaunay’s language of luminous, abstract forms.

Much of Delaunay’s work is more purely abstract, but this painting belongs to the series of female nudes – exceptional among Delaunay’s oeuvre – executed in Spain and Portugal, where the artist and his wife had withdrawn during World War I.

The overlapping constellation of circular motifs at the edges of the composition are more typical of his work and recalls the so-called room wheels of Michel Eugène Chevreul, the nineteenth century chemist whose theory of simultaneous room contrasts had also been a touchstone of Impressionism.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/197920_1_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>11</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>Portrait of James Carroll Beckwith</title>
		<author>Thomas Eakins</author>
		<description>1904
Size: 83 3/8 in. x 48 1/8 in. (211.8 cm x 122.2 cm)
Gift of Mrs. Thomas Eakins, 1937:30
After studying and painting in France and Spain, Thomas Eakins brought back to the United States what he learned in Europe and applied it to the life he knew in Philadelphia. He was an influential instructor at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts and even after his removal from the Academy, students continued to follow his innovative ideas and were enthusiastic about his encouragement to find inspiration in the people and places of the United States. Steadfast in his realism, Eakins was a controversial figure in his day but is today regarded among the most important of American artists.

This life-sized portrait is typical of Eakins’s later works in which the subject emerges dramatically from a dark background. The portrait depicts James Carroll Beckwith, an American painter known mainly for his portraits and romanticized female figures. Eakins depicts Beckwith in the act of painting one such work, a portrait of Mrs. Beckwith, who was also an artist.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/1937.30_0.jpeg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>12</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>The Hands of Dr. Moore</title>
		<author>Diego Rivera</author>
		<description>1940
Size: 18 in. x 22 in. (45.7 cm x 55.9 cm)
Bequest of Mrs. E. Clarence Moore, 1970:20
© 2012 Banco de México Diego Rivera Frida Kahlo Museums Trust, Mexico, D.F. / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York
In this non-traditional portrait, Diego Rivera chose to focus on the doctor’s hands instead of creating a more typical image that featured the sitter’s face. The inscription reads, “These are the hands of Dr. Clarence Moore of Los Angeles, California. They trim the tree of life so that it is renewed and does not die. Diego Rivera painted them in 1940.”

With its reference to roots, female anatomy, and blood, and through the use of a ribbon-like banner that includes an inscription, the painting recalls the work of Frida Kahlo, a Mexican artist whom Rivera twice married.

The anthropomorphic tree that is transformed from a symbol of the natural world to the female figure reflects the status of the tree as an iconic symbol in Mexican art history from pre-Columbian to contemporary times. Moreover the tree motif appears in the Museum’s other painting by Rivera, the Mandrágora of 1939, and in such works as Pan American Unity, also created in 1940, and permanently on view at San Francisco City College.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_300w/197020_2_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>13</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Jean Arp</title>
		<author>Arnold Newman</author>
		<description>1949
Size: 9 7/8 in. x 11 3/4 in. (25.1 cm x 29.8 cm)
Gift of Jordan Finn, 2008:22
One of the twentieth century’s most renowned portrait photographers, Arnold Newman is best known for his series of environmental portraits, in which the photographer captured his subjects in settings that expressed their life and work. His most famous images are of artists, writers, and politicians, but Newman was insistent that his compositions be interesting photographs and not merely records of celebrities’ appearances.

In this typical example of Newman’s work, one of many Newman portraits in the Museum’s collection, he has juxtaposed the sculptor Jean Arp with one of Arp’s own abstract sculptures.

Given the light-sensitive nature of photographic prints, The San Diego Museum of Art displays the collection of photography in rotating displays that change every few months. Visitors can, nonetheless, always find an installation of photography on view – either works from the collection or a loan exhibition.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/2008.22_1_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>14</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>Night Presence II</title>
		<author>Louise Nevelson</author>
		<description>1976
Size: 155 5/8 in. x 95 3/4 in. x 55 1/4 in. (395.3 cm x 243.2 cm x 140.3 cm)
Museum purchase through the Earle W. Grant Endowment Fund, 1976:137
© 2012 Estate of Louise Nevelson / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York
The outdoor May S. Marcy Sculpture Court, adjacent the Museum’s main building, is a must-see for monumental art.  Under cover of the Sculpture Court Café stands Louise Nevelson’s Night Presence II of 1976, an arresting meditation on architecture composed of columns, finials and scroll-sawed steel offcuts.

Experimenting first with wall-mounted assemblages of found objects, mostly wood, which the artist painted either all black or all white to unify her three-dimensional compositions, Nevelson began in the 1960s to translate these reliefs into freestanding sculptures.  The use of welded Cor-Ten steel, its oxidized patina a rusty red, allowed Nevelson to install her work outdoors, her boxy abstractions recalling oversized Cubist collages.

In contrast to Night Presence II’s forest of standing forms, the sculpture court also showcases Henry Moore’s Reclining Figure: Arch Leg of 1969, alongside works by such sculptors as Barbara Hepworth and David Smith.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_300w/1976137Nevelson_0.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>15</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>Flin Flon VIII</title>
		<author>Frank Stella</author>
		<description>1970
Size: 108 in. x 108 in. (274.3 cm x 274.3 cm)
Museum purchase, 1979:19
© 2012 Frank Stella / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York
Frank Stella first came into prominence in 1959, when his spare, black-and-white canvases were featured in a seminal show at the Museum of Modern Art, and he emerged in the 1960s as one of the leading figures of American Abstraction. 

In marked contrast to the paradigm of painting as a magic window, Stella advanced a more literal, concrete conception of the painted surface as a pattern bounded by edges. His shaped canvases of concentric black-and-white bands set the stage for the Minimalist movement, but Stella began in the later 1960s to integrate room into his increasingly monumental compositions. One of a series of paintings that explored relationships of room, form and pattern, Flin Flon VIII’s petal-like geometric shapes– made of overlapping protractor outlines– seem to project and recede in a dizzying optical dance.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/197919Stella.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>16</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>Spinal Column</title>
		<author>Alexander Calder</author>
		<description>1968
Size: 118 in. x 100 in. x 90 in. (299.7 cm x 254 cm x 228.6 cm)
Museum purchase with funds provided by Mr. and Mrs. Norton S. Walbridge, 1969:2
© 2012 Calder Foundation, New York / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York
Alexander Calder’s works– both his kinetic mobiles and his large painted iron stabiles– transformed entirely the nature of public sculpture in the United States. While inspired by the early experiments in purely abstract art that Calder witnessed during his early visits to Europe, Calder’s stabiles often play with references to forms from the natural world.

Spinal Column, for example, is at first glance a series of non-representational curves slicing through space, but on further examination seems a fanciful play on the vertebrae of the human backbone. Commissioned for The San Diego Museum of Art in 1968, Spinal Column long stood with other large scale twentieth-century works in the Museum’s May S. Marcy Sculpture Court but has recently been reinstalled on the front steps of the Museum.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/19692_1_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>17</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>La Jolla Cove</title>
		<author>Alfred R. Mitchell</author>
		<description>ca. 1950
Size: 24 in. x 36 in. (60.9 cm x 91.4 cm)
Gift of the artist, 1965:26
After receiving his initial artistic education in San Diego under Maurice Braun, Alfred Mitchell studied at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts and traveled in Europe before returning to California. He would later serve as President of the San Diego Art Guild and was among those who signed the incorporation papers for the Fine Arts Gallery of San Diego, which today is known as The San Diego Museum of Art.

Like many of his contemporary artists in Southern California, Mitchell combined in his work the lessons both of Thomas Eakins’s American Realism and of French art; the resulting plein air style has come to be known as California Impressionism. Visitors to The San Diego Museum of Art will find on display a group of California Impressionist paintings that includes Mitchell’s work alongside that of such artists as Maurice Braun, Nicolai Fechin, Charles Fries, Charles Reiffel, Guy Rose, and Elliott Torrey.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/196526.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>18</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>The White Flower</title>
		<author>Georgia O'Keeffe</author>
		<description>1932
Size: 29 3/4 in. x 39 3/4 in. (75.6 cm x 100.9 cm)
Gift of Mrs. Inez Grant Parker in memory of Earle W. Grant, 1971:12
© 2012 Georgia O'Keeffe Museum / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York
After studying at the Art Institute of Chicago, Georgia O’Keeffe spent time intermittently in New York City, where she met the photographer Alfred Stieglitz, who promoted her art. Though she created images of the urban environment in the 1920s, after 1929 O’Keeffe lived in New Mexico during the summer, and in 1946 she moved there permanently.

Much of her extensive artistic productions became focused on diverse elements of the natural world: animal bones, shells, desert, sky, and most frequently, flowers. She often enlarged flowers, making a single flower dominate the entire pictorial space. With The White Flower,O’Keeffe explores the beauty of nature and emphasizes formal qualities such as shape, room, and line.

The San Diego Museum of Art possesses three other works by the artist: Barn with Snow (1934), Purple Hills (1935), and In the Patio I (1946).
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/197112jpg.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>19</id>
		<room>room2</room>
		<title>Woman Reading</title>
		<author>Eastman Johnson</author>
		<description>ca. 1874
Size: 25 1/8 in. x 18 5/8 in. (63.8 cm x 47.3 cm)
Museum purchase with funds provided by the Gerald and Inez Grant Parker Foundation, 1977:9
Eastman Johnson created intimate scenes of daily life that contribute to our understanding of the American cultural landscape during his lifetime. Born in Lovell, Maine, Johnson lived mostly in New England, and this painting is likely one of the many works that were inspired by the landscape of Nantucket, Massachusetts.

Women figured prominently in Johnson’s work, and he frequently painted them alone and often engaged in tasks that were popular activities for women in the late 19th century, such as reading or walking outdoors.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/19779.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>20</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>In the Catskills</title>
		<author>Asher Brown Durand</author>
		<description>1848
Size: 30 in. x 42 1/4 in. (76.2 cm x 107.3 cm)
Museum purchase with funds provided by the Gerald and Inez Grant Parker Foundation, 1974:72
Asher B. Durand is best known today for his enduring images of the American landscape, especially of the Hudson River Valley, the Catskills, and the Adirondack Mountains in New York. A founding member of the National Academy of Design, he studied engraving before devoting himself to landscape painting and was one of the primary painters of the Hudson River School.

Durand’s canvases reflect the great passion and unrelenting respect he possessed for the natural environment. In the detailed charcoal study for Landscape-Composition: In the Catskills, which he probably made on site, Durand included the small figural forms in the foreground; in this, the final painting of the subject, these tiny figures, juxtaposed with the immensity of the mountains and the breadth of the land before them, emphasize the awe-inspiring presence of the land itself.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/197472_2_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>21</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>The Marques de Sofraga</title>
		<author>Francisco de Goya</author>
		<description>ca. 1795
Size: 42 5/8 in. x 32 1/2 in. (108.3 cm x 82.5 cm)
Gift of Anne R. and Amy Putnam, 1938:244
Francisco de Goya was an artist of remarkable talents, responsible for works ranging from altarpieces to nudes, from brutally realistic images of war to the horrifying and visionary scenes of his print series. The most highly sought portraitist in Madrid, Goya served as the official painter to the Spanish Court.

The Marqués de Sofraga, among the most powerful of Goya’s portraits, was probably commissioned to celebrate the sitter’s appointment as director of the Royal Academy of History in 1794. The Marqués is shown in his most official attire, but as in the greatest of portraits, Goya mitigates between his own artistic ambitions and the visual propaganda desired by the sitter. The sitter’s medals, for example, would have been immediately recognizable to contemporaries as markers of status, but Goya has painted them in an almost impressionistic technique; the Golden Fleece at Sofraga’s breast is reduced to daubs of paint.

Likewise, while there can be no question of the sitter’s importance, there is something chilling in the Marqués’s heavy-lidded gaze. Goya’s penetrating view of human psychology – fully evident in this masterpiece – has few equals in the history of portraiture.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/1938244_0.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>22</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Radha comes to Krishna</title>
		<author>Ruknuddin</author>
		<description>1685
Size: 7 5/8 in. x 5 9/32 in. (19.4 cm x 13.4 cm)
Edwin Binney 3rd Collectionof South Asian paintings, 1990:786
This painting is one of nearly 2,000 works in The San Diego Museum of Art's world-class Edwin Binney 3rd Collection of Indian paintings. A selection from this collection is always on view in the Museum’s galleries.

Written in Hindi by Keshavdas in 1591, the Rasikapriya classifies heroes and heroines in different stages of maturity or experience and describes their varying reactions to similar situations.  Most of the attention is given to the reactions of heroines, who are cleverly analyzed in circumstances caused by the hero (the blue Krishna every time), as a very aggressive lover, and often a philanderer.  Keshavdas describes 360 circumstances of love. He composed the work to entertain his patron, the Raja of Orchha.

The episodes usually involve not only the hero and heroine (Krishna and Radha) but her female companions, or sakhis, as well.  They serve as confidantes and messengers for the lovers.  In the upper register Radha is longing for the stand-offish Krishna, and with the advice of the sakhis, boldly takes the initiative, going to him with her vina to please him with music.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/1990.786_1_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>23</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Quince, Cabbage, Melon, and Cucumber</title>
		<author>Juan Sanchez Cotan</author>
		<description>ca. 1602
Size: 27 1/8 in. x 33 1/4 in. (68.9 cm x 84.5 cm)
 
Gift of Anne R. and Amy Putnam, 1945:43
Still-life painting was virtually nonexistent in European art before the 1590s, and Sánchez Cotán is considered not only among the first practitioners of the genre, but also arguably the greatest. This work, moreover, is universally acclaimed as his masterpiece.

Brilliantly executed, the painting is unflinching in its naturalism and simplicity. The mysterious serenity of the composition, in which the objects are positioned in a perfect curve against the deep black background, has led many to question the meaning or function of the image. For some, the work is an exercise in pure painting, the straightforward depiction of vegetables in a cold cellar. Others, however, believe that the picture may have religious overtones, and that it should be understood as a celebration of God’s most humble creations. In support of the latter reading, it is often noted that Sánchez Cotán gave up his possessions and entered a Carthusian monastery soon after painting this canvas.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_550w/194543_0.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>24</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Hayagriva</title>
		<author>Artist Unknown</author>
		<description>15th century, Tibet
Size: 16 1/4 in. x 12 1/2 in. x 5 3/4 in. (41.28 cm x 31.75 cm x 14.61 cm)
Museum purchase with funds provided by the Elsie S. Kimberly Bequest, 1968:17
In the Tibetan Buddhist context, Hayagriva is one of eight major bodhisattvas who take on the wrathful form of a guardian of sacred knowledge.  Through rituals and prayer, Buddhists can invoke Hayagriva and use his power to help them conquer obstacles to enlightenment.

The name Hayagriva means “He who has the Neck of a Horse;” accordingly, he has three diminutive horses’ necks and heads emerging from his hair. His mouth is open, because it is through sound – his terrifying neigh – that Hayagriva dispels demons and afflictions.  Under his feet he tramples either snakes or personifications of the causes of mental suffering. The garland of multi-roomed severed heads (symbolizing the eradication of one's deluded sense of self) and inset jewels are typical of sculptures associated with the Indian tantric tradition.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_300w/196817.jpg.crop_display_0.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

	<artwork>
		<id>25</id>
		<room>room1</room>
		<title>Portrait of Mrs. Robert Henri</title>
		<author>Robert Henri</author>
		<description>August 1914
Size: 24 in. x 20 in. (60.9 cm x 50.8 cm)
Gift of Mrs. George Heyneman, 1959:7
Robert Henri studied at both the Académie Julian and the École des Beaux-Arts in Paris and at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts. Though Thomas Eakins was no longer teaching at the Academy when Henri arrived, Eakins was immensely influential for Henri, who regarded him as the superior portrait painter in the United States and followed Eakins’s bluntly realist style.

This painting of Robert Henri’s second wife, Marjorie Organ Henri, was given by the artist to Alice Klauber, who studied with Henri in Spain in 1907. Klauber invited Henri to San Diego in 1914, and he assisted her with the organization of an exhibition of American painting for the 1915 Panama-California Exposition, which was held in what became Balboa Park. The exhibition brought the work of George Bellows, William Glackens, Childe Hassam, John Sloan, and Henri to San Diego.
		</description>
		<vidurl>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hmWWfnKVbYY</vidurl>
		<imgurl>http://www.sdmart.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/must_see_300w/19597_1.jpg</imgurl>
	</artwork>

</mobilegallery>

